<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The soules ingrafting into Christ. By T.H.</title>
            <author>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03610</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13733</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104199</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839938</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839938</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03610)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1072:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The soules ingrafting into Christ. By T.H.</title>
                  <author>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] H[aviland] for Andrew Crooke, at the signe of the Beare in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.H. = Thomas Hooker.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The title page in largely in the same setting as the sub title page of STC 13739.</note>
                  <note>Text differs from that of the longer treatise of the same title included in his "The soules implantation".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Redemption --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4400:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SOVLES INGRAFTING into CHRIST.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>Andrew Crooke,</hi> at the ſigne of the Beare in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1637.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4400:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4400:2"/>
            <head>THE SOVLES Ingrafting into CHRIST.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MAL. 3.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold, I will ſend my Meſſenger, and hee ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the way before mee, and the Lord whom yee ſeeke ſhall ſuddenly come to his Temple: even the Meſſenger of the Covenant whom yee delight in: Behold hee ſhall come, ſaith the Lord of Hosts.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the Preface two things are conſiderable. 1. What wee have done. 2. What wee will doe. We have finiſhed the ſcope of our endevour, which was to ſhew how Chriſts Merits are applied to the Soule, how it ſtands poſſeſſed of grace here and happineſſe hereafter. Now theſe two things muſt be wrought in the Soule, before it can be made partaker of ſaving grace: 1. A preparation. 2. an Implantation. A preparation there muſt be,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> for a ſinner naturally as he hath no grace, ſo hee
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4400:3"/> is not naturally capable to receive grace. This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in 2. things: 1. On Gods part, he breakes the curſed Combination betwixt Sinne and the Soule, hee drawes us from ſinne to himſelfe. 2. Something on our part touching the diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our hearts: and that in 2. workes. 1. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, 2. Humiliation. Now there was a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of theſe two to be in the Soule, as wee then diſputed, for theſe are the two maine hinderan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of our Faith: 1. Security, when the ſoule being blinded takes reſt and ſees no need to be better, therefore deſires it not, hence naturall men thinke it Curioſity, therefore the Lord ſends in this worke, and cauſeth us to know the miſery of ſinne, and pierces our ſoules with it, and ſo upon this we deſire a change, for elſe it ſees it muſt be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> condemned. 2. When the ſinner thus ſees his miſery, then he begins to ſcramble for his owne comforts, that he may releeve himſelfe, hee will reforme ſinne and doe ſuperficiall duties, and ſo thinke to make amends, this is Carnall confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, thus many a man periſheth, reſting on theſe huskes, for Meanes are not Mediatours, and Services are not Saviours; Now in the place thereof God diſcovers that there is ſinne enough in the beſt ſervices. The Soule being thus plucked off from ſin and from all his luſts, and pared from his abilities, renouncing all confidences, and being nothing hee is fit for Chriſt to bee all in all unto him; thus farre we have gone. All this while the Soule is like the children of Iſrael partly wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring in the valley of Teares, partly wildring in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4400:3"/> the deſart of Humiliation. Egypt was a Type of a mans naturall condition, <hi>Moſes</hi> a Type of the Law, <hi>Ioſuah</hi> a Type of Chriſt, the wilderneſſe a Type of theſe two. Now the ſoule having paſſed through all theſe, is juſt upon the Coaſt of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan. The ſoule is like a graft, firſt, it is cut off, then pared, and then ingrafted: So Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition cuts us off, and Humiliation pares us. The next Point is, the ingrafting into the Lord Jeſus, the heart being thus prepared, it is implanted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the true vine, the Lord Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Touching the worke, wee will diſcover theſe 2. things:
<list>
                  <item>1. We will open it in generall.</item>
                  <item>2. We will diſcover the parts of it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>What it is in generall, our implantation into <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Chriſt, is the worke of the Spirit, whereby the humbled ſinner ſtands poſſeſſed of Chriſt, and is made partaker of the Spirituall good things in him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Things in the Deſcription.</p>
            <p>The humbled ſinner, for elſe nothing to doe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> with Chriſt, ſtands poſſeſſed of Chriſt, I uſe the word poſſeſſor, becauſe it is rather wrought upon the ſoule, than comes out of any Principle in the ſoule; <hi>Chriſt poſſeſſes him, and hence hee comes to bee poſſeſſed,</hi> Gal. 4.9. as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>It is not, how wee can perceive him, but how hee will know us. Philip.</hi> 3.12. Still a man is more paſſive than active, the worke lyes on Gods part. The childe holds the father, becauſe the father holds him. So we hold God, becauſe he holds vs.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4400:4"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Hee is made partaker of the good things in Chriſt, ſtill the action lyes on Chriſts part, wee worke ſo far, as we are wrought on.</p>
            <p>Theſe two things are generall in all the workes of application. 1. To be poſſeſſed of Chriſt: 2. To be made partaker of the Spirituall good in him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> As in vocation, Chriſt drawes the ſoule, hee challenges more of him, than the being poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the ſoule following him there is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall good.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In Juſtification, Chriſt layes downe a price, there is the poſſeſſion, and withall, the ſoule is freed from the guilt and puniſhment of ſinne; there is the ſpirituall good.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In Adoption, Chriſt, not onely cals a ſinner, and juſtifies him, but adopts him, and makes him of a ſinner a ſonne, there is a nearer poſſeſſion, and he hath the privileges of a ſonne; there is the Spirituall good derived from Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> In Sanctification, the Lord Chriſt, by the power of his Spirit leaves a ſtampe of his Image, grace for grace, he is marked for his owne, this is the further poſſeſſion; he is freed from the power of corruption; this is the Spirituall good. Thus in all we ſee, the ſoule is poſſeſſed of Chriſt, hee is partaker of the Spirituall good in him.</p>
            <p>All this is done by Gods Spirit: a graft cannot put it ſelfe into the ſtocke, but the ſame hand that cut it off, and pared it, muſt ingraft it, to the ſame Spirit that wrought Contrition, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, comes to bee the Spirit of grace and promiſe. Now for the ground of our diſcourſe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4400:4"/> wee have choſen this Text, which is a Prophecie of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt.</p>
            <p>Wherein obſerve 2. things.</p>
            <p>The words are ſpoken of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Conſider the worke of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, he was the Meſſenger of God, and was to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the way for Chriſt. 2. We have the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, <hi>The Lord will ſuddenly come into his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> We come to the point, but before I can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the ſeverall particulars, give me leave to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen two words, that ſo the doctrine may bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, what is meant by Temple. 2. What, by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Chriſts comming into the Temple.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the word Temple, beſides the naturall and literall ſenſe of it, it is alſo taken Myſtically and Spiritually, and ſo it is here to be conceived, and then it implyes partly the Church of God, I meane the company of the faithfull which ſerve God in uprightneſſe of heart, and as in generall, all the company of the people fearing God, are ſaid, to be the Church of God, and his Temple, ſo alſo in particular, every man that is faithfull, is the Temple of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Yee are the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Looke as it was in the materiall Temple in Jeruſalem, the text ſaith, <hi>the Glory of the Lord fell upon it,</hi> and the Lord ſaid, <hi>he would abide there, and reveale himſelfe there,</hi> ſo the heart humbled and prepared is the Temple of the Lord, and the Lord takes poſſeſſion of it, and rules in it, and will provide for it for ever. Looke as a man dwels in a houſe prepared for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4400:5"/> him, ſo the Lord dwels in a humbled Soule. Thus we have ſhewed what is meant by Temple.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> What is meant by the comming of the Lord into his Temple: as the Temple was Spiritually to bee conceived, ſo is this comming. By com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, is here meant, when the Lord comes to take poſſeſſion of the Soule truly prepared, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it that the Lord Chriſt comes as a King, therefore he hath a Harbinger before him, hee hath one to prepare all things for him.</p>
            <p>A King comes 2. waies, firſt he takes ſoveraigne poſſeſſion at the place where hee is; If he come to a towne or to an Inne, the Gueſts that tooke up the place, muſt be gone: ſo the Lord comes as a King, he comes to take ſoveraigne poſſeſſion of the Soule. 2. All Kings bring furniture with them, when he comes to a place, his owne fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture muſt bee hung up. So Chriſt comes theſe 2. wayes, he takes full poſſeſſion of the ſoule, and provides mercifully for the ſoule. Thus wee have the words opened, and now the point is plaine enough. The Engliſh of the text is this: When <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, by the power of the Word and Spirit of Contrition, and Humiliation, hath laid the Soules of Gods ſervants, humbled and willing to be at Gods diſpoſe, then ſuddenly and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly, the Lord Jeſus will come, and hee will command as a King, and take poſſeſſion of an humble Soule, and provide gratiouſly for it, hee comes to the naked wals, he brings his proviſion with him, he cares for nothing but a Soule pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared and emptied, and he will bring proviſion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4400:5"/> enough of Vocation, Adoption, Juſtification, and Sanctification: now we will gather the points as they lye.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> That the Lord Jeſus cannot be hindred from comming into an humbled Soule.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> That the Lord Chriſt takes poſſeſſion of the Soule, as a King, and will provide for it.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, that Chriſt cannot bee hindred from comming into a Soule truly humbled, hee commeth ſpeedily, as who ſhould ſay, he layeth all other worke aſide, as though he cared for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, lookt after nothing, intended after no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but how all might come into the heart prepared: the wicked of the world, he will not come at them; though the rich crie, he will not heare them; though the honorable periſh, he will not looke after them; but the Lord will come ſuddenly into an humble Soule, nay, to ſpeake with reverence, he leaves all Company, he leaves Heaven and the bleſſed Angels, he leaves all, and onely deſires to be in, and to live with an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble broken heart, it is the manner of the Phraſe; he comes ſuddenly, as who ſhould ſay, he lets all alone, he cares for nothing, go he muſt, and take poſſeſſion of a broken Soule; this is the cauſe that the Scripture doth not content it ſelfe, in expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the marvellous tender reſpect, that the Lord hath toward ſuch a Soule, the delight the Lord hath in an humble Soule, he will lie with a broken heart, and dwell with it, and ſleepe with it; he will ſuddenly come into his Temple, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.16. We may ſee it in the father of the prodigall: the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4400:6"/> prodigall he reſolved to returne to his father, and ſay, I have ſinned againſt Heaven and againſt thee, &amp;c. the father he obſerves this, that he is content to be at his diſpoſe, and hee lyeth at the doore, and deſires to come into his family, though his condition were baſe, and he was rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; the father he might ſay, go to your Queanes, let them comfort you if they can; no, the text ſaith, hee ſaw him a farre off, and hee ranne and had compaſſion on him, and fell upon his neck, and kiſſed him, before the prodigall could ſpeake a word, or kneele downe, he ranne, and kiſſed him.</p>
            <p>Obſerve here foure particulars: He ſaw him a farre off, and had compaſſion on him, ranne to meet him, and kiſſed him. Hee never now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members that he was riotous, a whorer, a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, that he had laviſhed out all his ſubſtance: all this was forgotten: but when he ſees him come humbly, and brokenly, he ſaw him a farre off, before the prodigall could ſee his father; nay hee compaſſioned his wretchedneſſe, before he could confeſſe it, nay, hee ranne to meet him more ſpeedily than he could come to him, and when the prodigall fell downe before him, hee fell on his necke and kiſſed him, before he could ſpeake a word; this Scripture doth not ſatisfie it ſelfe, it cannot tell how to expreſſe the marvellous ready inlargement of the Lord, to give entertainment to an humbled Soule, and it is remarkable, after the prodigall had ſaid, Father I have ſinned, &amp;c. Fetch out, ſaith he, the beſt robe; to cover him,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4400:6"/> and put a ring on his finger, &amp;c. As who ſhould ſay, Tis no matter for thy ſtubbornneſſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliouſneſſe; a prodigall thou haſt been, I care not for it, bring this robe to cover him, kill the fat Calfe to feed him, and the ring to adorne him. So <hi>Luke</hi> 15.4. A man that hath an hundred ſheepe, and one be gone aſtray, he leaves there 99. and he goes ſeeking for that, and when hee findes the ſtragling ſheep, though it cannot come home, he takes it upon his ſhoulder and brings it home: The loſt ſheepe is the loſt Soule, that is bee-wildred, the Lord Jeſus after all mercies vouchſafed to him, and kindneſſe enlarged to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him; yet the loſt ſheepe will be ſtragling, the Lord leaves all now to ſeeke him: and marke the phraſe and the degree thereof, he leaves all to ſeeke it, and will never leave till hee finde it, he doth not ſeeke hourely, but he ſeekes till hee hath found it; when he hath found it, he brings it home. The Lord will leave all, to ſeeke an humbled ſinner; the more need thou haſt of Chriſt, the more labor he will beſtow in ſeeking of thee, and he will never leave ſeeking, till hee hath found thee; and when he hath found thee, though thou canſt not goe, he will carry thee up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſhoulders, to everlaſting happineſſe. This is to expreſſe the marvellous readineſſe and bounty of the Lord, towards a poore humble ſinner, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.45. This is the ſcope of the Parable of the Pearle; the text ſaith, <hi>The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is like unto a Pearle, which when a Merchant had found, he ſeld all he had, and bought
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4400:7"/> it.</hi> Firſt, we will open the text, then apply it to our purpoſe. The Pearle is nothing elſe but the rich Mercy of God, and Grace, and Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Chriſt: the Merchant man is every poore ſinfull creature, that wants mercy to comfort him, and grace to pardon him; for what is all the world, if my Soule wants mercy? well he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth where the Pearle is; the bargaine is thus, he muſt ſell all and buy this Pearle: Hee comes to Gods tearmes, &amp; buyeth it at his rate, and there is no more words: this ſelling of all is, when a man parts with all ſinnes, and confidence in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: then he hath ſold all, when he will neither truſt to his owne worth, nor reſt in his owne ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, and ſeeth himſelfe miſerable by corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions committed, and ſeeth that he is unable to releeve himſelfe out of his miſery, and then hee is willing to part with all; and when hee hath done this, then there is no more words to the bargaine, but the Lord bids him take the Pearle, he hath bought it, and carry it away with him: ſo then the caſe is cleere, if you bee good chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and bid roundly, and come to Gods price, there is no more words to the bargaine. You would have ſinne and Chriſt, God and Devill; no, no, but ſell all and the pearle is yours: you may take it in your hand, and carry it home with you: thus much for the proofe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> I come now to the Reaſons, whence comes it, that the Lord will not delay to come into an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoule, the marvellous readineſſe of the Lord, it is admirable to thinke on it: the reaſons are three:</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:4400:7"/>
            <p>Becauſe the Lord Jeſus was ſent, for this very <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> end, by God the Father, <hi>Matt.</hi> 15.24. And hee came alſo to this very purpoſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.10. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up the places. I am not ſent, but to the loſt ſheepe of Iſrael; and in the other place, there he came to ſeeke, and ſave that which was loſt, that is, loſt in the ſight and ſenſe of his owne miſery, loſt in regard of his owne ability and ſufficiency to helpe himſelfe: Then laſtly, willing to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by another, this is the nature of a loſt man. The man that is in the wilderneſſe, if hee knew not the way out, there is no meanes to ſuccour him; therefore he is willing and contented, that any man ſhould direct him the way out: if a man ſhould ſay, this is the path that leads you out of the wilderneſſe to ſuch a place, would hee not yeeld to his advice, hee were but a loſt man; ſo doſt thou ſee, that thou art loſt, if thou lieſt in the wilderneſſe of ſinne, thou art a damned man; and then loſt, doſt thou ſee that thou art unable to come out and ſuccour thy ſelfe, art thou conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be informed by God, and diſpoſed by him, then marke what the text ſaith: The Sonne of man, the Lord Jeſus came to ſeeke ſuch ſinners, and the Lord will never leave till he finde thee, and when hee hath found thee, hee will never leave till hee hath ſaved thee: the Lord, though thou canſt not ſeeke him, hee will ſeeke thee; and when hee hath ſought thee, hee will ſave thee too. Then if the end of Chriſts comming, and the ſcope of his ſending, be to ſave a loſt ſinner, then above all, hee will attaine his owne end, fulfill
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4400:8"/> what was betruſted to him, hee will ſeeke and ſave him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond ground.</note>Becauſe an humble broken ſoule, is the fitteſt ſubject to ſet forth the glory of the riches of Gods grace and Salvation, that is in Chriſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, and through Chriſt conveyed to the ſoule: I ſay they are the fitteſt ſubjects for God to worke upon, for the Lord to come to and dwell in, and to ſet forth the honour of the worke of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as it deſerves, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.11.12. The text ſaith, hee worketh all things according to the counſell of his will, and why ſo? namely, to the praiſe of the glory of his grace. Now obſerve it, there is no ſoule ſo fit to ſet forth the praiſe of the glory of the grace of the Lord, and the great worke of Salvation, as a broken ſoule, and ſelfe denying heart: for an humble ſoule denies all in it ſelfe, but expects all from grace, and the free favour of God. It ſaith, it is unworthy to receive mercy, that it needs and beggs, and therefore an humble ſoule is the fitteſt of all to ſet forth the great worke of God, all the Councell of God; to ſet forth the riches of his grace, that all may be ſaid to be grace, as in that of <hi>Zacharie,</hi> when the temple was built, thy cryed, <hi>Grace, Grace, Grace,</hi> as who ſhould ſay, grace layeth the firſt ſtone, and grace layeth the laſt ſtone; all is of grace, from begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ending: ſo an humble ſoule ſetteth forth the freeneſſe of Gods grace abundantly, and ſaith, I deſerved nothing but hell, and if I have any thing but hell, it is from Gods mercy. But a proud heart, hee oppoſeth the worke of God; all the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4400:8"/> workmanſhip of the grace of God: The proud heart will have ſomething of it ſelfe, and take ſomething to it ſelfe to boaſt of, and where is grace now? it's not grace, but your parts and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities that you attribute all to, and by that meanes hinder the ſetting forth the riches of Gods mercy in Chriſt: Therefore an humble ſoule is the beſt ſhop, wherein the great worke of redemption, and frame of ſalvation may be ſeene: the poore ſoule will ſay, Looke what the Lord hath done, and it is marvellous in our eyes, it ought to be marvellous in our hearts. Looke as it is with men; No wiſe man will dwell in an houſe, where his credit may not be maintained, and where hee may not have all conveniences neceſſary, and therefore no marvell though Chriſt comes into an humble heart, it is the fitteſt place for the credit of Chriſt: Chriſt would worke all in the ſoule; the humble ſoule is content, he ſhall take notice of it. It is a ſchoole rule, there is no wiſe man that diſpoſeth of the frame of a building, but if he hath diſpoſed of it, he will ſet it up, and dwell in it, unleſſe he wants power or wiſdome; power, in that he hath begun a thing, and was not able to finiſh it; none of theſe can befall God: God is a wiſe ſufficient cauſe, hee never diſpoſeth of a matter fully, but he brings a frame and a forme to the matter diſpoſed: Now when the Lord hath prepared a building, and framed an humble ſoule to dwell in, if hee will not finiſh his frame, hee muſt want power and wiſdome: But theſe cannot be wanting, to an almighty, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4400:9"/> moſt wiſe God, therefore hee that hath fitted the heart for his owne credit, and for all conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, that all may be wrought by him, and all glory may come to him, ſurely that powerfull God, that cannot be hindred, and that wiſe God, that doth nothing but out of wiſedome, hee will reare up the building of grace, and ſalvation ſhall be beſtowed upon the ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The third ground.</note>Becauſe now all hinderances are taken out of the way that ſhould ſtop him, and all impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that ſhould let him, are removed wholly, therefore the place being for him, and he ready to come, he muſt of neceſſity come: for if there be any hinderance, to ſtop the comming of Chriſt into the ſoule; it muſt either lie on his part or on our part, but it ſhall appeare that there is no hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance either on Gods part, or a broken ſoules part, therefore there is nothing can hinder the Lord from comming: if there be any thing on our parts to hinder him, it is either becauſe wee love our ſelves, or cleave to our ſinnes: Now a broken heart hath renounced both theſe; an humble ſoule ſaith, ſinne ſhall not rule in mee; and a ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying heart ſaith, I cannot rule my ſelfe, and therefore Lord guide mee with thy grace, now the way is ready, the ſoule is divorced from all other matches, therefore it is ready for the Lord; the humbled ſoule hath renounced ſinne, and all authority of it ſelfe, and would have Chriſt rule over it: Now therefore all impediments muſt be on Chriſts part, that which cannot be, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.20. Our Saviour Chriſt is ſo farre from being
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4400:9"/> unwilling to come into the ſoule, that he ſtands knocking at the doore; hee knocks at a proud looſe heart, at a baſe drunken heart, Forſake theſe ſinnes, and entertaine a Saviour: renounce theſe corruptions, and entertaine thy owne ſalvation: be not under the power of corruption, that will undoe thee, but ſubmit to Chriſt, that will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme thee: Hee knocks and knocks againe, <hi>Open my Love, my Dove, my undefiled one:</hi> the Lord knocks thus at the doore; therefore if the doore be open, he will ſurely come in: nay he prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth himſelfe, <hi>I ſtand at the doore and knock:</hi> hee hath ſtood often at the heart of many ſtubborne ſinners, and knocked by mercies and judgements, and knocked by the word, and all bleſſings hee hath beſtowed, and ſaith, <hi>If any will open, I will come in and dwell with him.</hi> Now then, he that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth, that if the doore be open, hee will come in, if the doore be open, that hee may come, there is no unreadineſſe in him to come into the ſoule, but in an humbled ſoule, the doore is open, away ſinne, away ſelfe, I truſt you not, let the Lord come and rule in, &amp; take poſſeſſion of the heart of mine; the doore is wide open now, and the Lord knocked before, is glad to take the occaſion, and comes ſpeedily into the ſoule prepared and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. So then if it be the end of the ruling and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, if the glory of his mercy bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced thereby, if there be no hindrance, neither on our parts, or on Chriſts part; then the ſoule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus diſpoſed, immediately expect our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, for hee will come. Thus much for the proofe.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:4400:10"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> I confeſſe, nothing ſhould be deare (and if I know my ſelfe) there is no ſinne, but I am content it ſhould be looſened from mee, my ſinne I have abandoned, my ſelfe I have renounced, and yet I find no comfort, ſo that this doctrine is not true, or my heart not cured.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Is it thus with thee? then Chriſt is come, but thou perceiveſt it not. When <hi>Iacob</hi> awaked out of his ſleepe, <hi>Surely</hi> (ſaid hee) <hi>the Lord is in this place, and I perceived it not:</hi> And ſo the Lord is in thy ſoule, and thou perceiveſt him not.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But can Chriſt be, and not be ſeene?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I, tis too too often, and the hindrances are of two ſorts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. On our part.</item>
               <item>2. On Chriſts part.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Thoſe on our parts, are of foure ſorts.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Chriſt is come into thy ſoule, and thou doſt not know him. <hi>Matt.</hi> 14.26. When Chriſt was neareſt to comfort &amp;c. they thought it had beene a ſpirit to terrifie them. So thou ſaieſt, thy ſinnes are ugly to thee, thou thinkeſt this is not Chriſt, but it is: Jeſus Chriſt is there, and thou ſeeſt it not. <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.15.16. The poore ſoule of the woman longed for Chriſts ſociety, and ſhee thinking it had beene a gardner, enquired of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, for a Saviour: So a broken hearted ſinner ſeekes a Saviour; if you know how I may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine favour with God, counſell a poore ſinner. It is Chriſt that gives thee the heart to ſeeke him, and that Chriſt thou ſeekeſt: by the vertue of a Saviour, thou ſeekeſt for a Saviour, as a man lookes for a candle, by the light of his candle. <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.9.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:4400:10"/>
            <p>Thou attendeſt not to our Saviour when hee <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> comes; hee that comes, quietly conveies himſelfe, and thou ſeeſt him not: as to his Diſciples, when they were all ſhut up in a Chamber, then hee appeared in the midſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24. <hi>Why ſeekeſt thou the living among the dead.</hi> So wee rub the ſore day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and thinke, can grace come into ſuch a heart: Whilſt thou art thus looking on corruption, thou canſt not ſee Chriſt: <hi>Why ſeekeſt thou the living a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the dead,</hi> why ſeekeſt thou a Saviour to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thee, among corruptions that would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thee. It was not the fault in <hi>Hagars</hi> eyes, that ſhee ſaw not the fountaine, but ſhee attended not to it; ſo wee ſit diſconſolate, and Chriſt is in us, but wee looke not after him: A man that waits for a Noble-man; if hee come not at the houre appointed, hee goes into a corner and weepes, becauſe hee thinks he hath taken diſtaſte, and this, whilſt the Noble-man approaches, and is there a great while, before hee knowes it; ſo while wee goe drooping under our corruptions, the Lord Chriſt comes not, and wee goe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, and in the mean time Chriſt comes, and wee ſee him not. Hee that goes in a dungeon ſhall never ſee Sun-ſhine, though it ſhine never ſo cleerely; ſo when this Sonne of Righteouſneſſe ſhines, wee goe into the dungeon of diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo perceive him not, though hee ſhines moſt cleerely.</p>
            <p>Wee alſo are not able aright to know when <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Chriſt is in us: becauſe wee judge him by ſenſe, and ſome extraordinary ſweetneſſe, wee imagine
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4400:11"/> ſhould be in us: woe judge upon falſe grounds; every ſinner ſets up a fancie in his owne Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that if Chriſt comes, ſtrange matters will be wrought. Now framing this fancie in his conceit, he will take no other evidence of Chriſts comming.</p>
            <p>It was the fault of <hi>Gideon, Iudges</hi> 6.13. he judges Gods preſence there, upon falſe grounds; for hee was with him, as well to helpe him beare the miſery, as to deliver him from it; ſo it is with an humble ſinner burthened with the ſight of his abominations; when the Miniſters ſay, The Lord is with you, you broken ſinners, they reply, If the Lord be with us, why is all his befalne us: what, ſay ſome, diſtempers ſo violent, corruptions ſo many, and can the Lord be here? where are thoſe miracles the Saints heretofore have found? Behold what God did for <hi>David,</hi> for <hi>Elias,</hi> for <hi>Paul,</hi> they led captivity captive, and were more than Conquerors over their corruptions, and yet wee are burthened with our ſins. I anſwer, the Lord is as well preſent to helpe thee contend againſt ſinne, as to make thee domineere over it. The ſame Apoſtle that was more than Conqueror at one time, was led captive at another, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23. And had the fleſh luſting againſt the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. This is your conceit; you thinke if the King come, there will be no Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours; but Traitors will follow the Court: you thinke if the King come to your harts, hee muſt needs promote you to ſome place of honour. This is the apprehenſion of a broken heart: Were
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4400:11"/> Chriſt in mee, then I ſhould have ſuch and ſuch ſufficiency; theſe are deſperate miſtakes, <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.25. It is a patterne of a broken Soule that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon ſome ſtirring apprehenſion, if I had that ability, if my heart could ſo breake, if I had ſuch aſſurance, then Chriſt were come: You will not beleeve the King is come, unleſſe hee hug you in his boſome. Thus wee judge according to ſenſe, not according to the promiſe of Chriſt, who is bleſſed for ever: It befalls the Soule as <hi>Iacob, Gen.</hi> 45.24. Hee would not beleeve their word; but when hee ſaw their Chariots, then he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of it: this is the frame of diſconſolate ſpirits. Wee have the word of God, to confirme the preſence of Chriſt, unleſſe you be Charioted with that ability, as to triumph over all ſinnes, your ſpirits are not revived, you beleeve not that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is yet alive, your Saviour is with you.</p>
            <p>When our eyes are held, namely when the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſting of Conſcience ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, or when the fierceneſſe of temptation preſſes in, or elſe when ſome world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inconvenience ſits cloſe, ſo that the thoughts of a mans heart are wholly beſtowed upon that object, the Soule cannot owne Chriſt, though he were cloſe by him. A man that hath his heart ſwayed with ſad meditations, though hee meet with a man of his acquaintance, yet hee would not know him: So it was with the diſciples, looke <hi>Luke</hi> 24. <hi>verſ.</hi> 32. <hi>Did not our hearts burne in us;</hi> as who ſhould ſay, there was teſtimony enough, of a divine preſence, it was a Chriſt that ſpake, but wee were not able to ſee it: So when
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4400:12"/> the ſoule is taken up with two hurries, partly with temptation, partly with worldly occaſions, it ſees not Chriſt, though the heart burnes towards him: this is the ground, why, when Satan lets flie, though wee propound never ſo many promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, alwayes thoſe perplexed Spirits forget what is ſpoken, and their minde is only upon temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: They attend not Chriſt in the promiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their eyes are held, though they be in their privie Chamber, and may talke with our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 13.23.</p>
            <p>The Lord Jeſus, out of our juſt deſert, doth hide himſelfe, <hi>Eſay</hi> 8.17. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 31.22. Now Chriſt hides himſelfe in theſe three caſes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> When the Saints fall into ſome foule groſſe ſin, or elſe are at truce with ſome boſome corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though but an infirmitie, then God doth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his preſence, for obedience is the tearme of Gods preſence, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.1. Hee is with us, while we are with him: If then the Saints breake company, no marvell though Chriſt withdraw his ſociety, <hi>Iohn</hi> 19.21. This is the tenure of Chriſts manifeſtation, provided wee love him; but if not, hee is gone, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 51. <hi>Create a new Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within mee,</hi> (as who ſhould ſay) all is to begin a new. This God doth ſo ſhew his indignation againſt ſinne, hee will not beare nor bolſter it, no not in his owne, and this God doth not only when they ſin fouly, but when they are at truce with a diſtemper, though but an Infirmity: as for example, if a Chriſtian be overtaken ordinarily with a cholerick diſtemper, if a Chriſtian be eager
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4400:12"/> of the world, or growes dead in ſervices, it is juſt with God, that theſe men ſhould be deſtitute of their comforts.</p>
            <p>When the Saints of God grow wanton, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the ſenſe and ſweetneſſe of the feeling of his favour, thereupon growing careleſſe, now God ſeeing a man abuſing his goodneſſe, it is juſt with him to eſtrange himſelfe from that Soule, that hee may labour for his former ſtrength againe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 30.6.</p>
            <p>The Lord hides himſelfe by way of preventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> as thus; hee will not make ſome of his to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend his favour, leſt they ſhould pranck up themſelves in the privilege, and cenſoriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne their fellow brethren; but holds out the heart at the ſtaffe end, ſo much mercy as may ſerve his turne, that hee may be a little comforted, and yet humbled. If the Father ſee the child grow proud, hee keeps him upon dependance, that he may have better obedience. So God ſees wee have unruly hearts, and therefore keeps us upon dependance, that hee may have more obedience, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.12. If there were high ſailes upon a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Barke, they would drowne it in ſtead of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying of it: So men proportion their ſailes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Barke. This is one maine ground, why God takes away the ſenſe of his favour: The Sea is the world, the Soule ſailes about, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle gale carrieth it on, but if it ſhould have great ſailes, they would drowne it; not that grace doth this, the fault is not in the ſailes, but in the boat that will not beare, &amp;c. So the fault is not in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4400:13"/> grace, but in the Soule, that cannot beare it: This is the reaſon why many men have ſmoken out their dayes in ſorrow, and at their death have great aſſurance: It was the ſpeech of a good man, that God will not alwayes give his ſervants a cup of Sack; his meaning was, hee would not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes comfort them; the comforts of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit are better than wine, now much of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort with a proud heart, would cauſe him to tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon every man: Therefore God keeps the cup to the laſt. If while therefore God keeps us under hatches, if while hee withdrawes his hand, wee doe contend with the Almighty, and often ſay, why ſhould I pray, and God anſwers not, heare and God accepts not? if when wee are kept low, and doe thus, if then wee had what wee would, certainly wee would turne our backs to the Almighty and ſay, as they in <hi>Ieremy</hi> 2.31. <hi>Wee will come no more unto thee:</hi> Therefore it is good for God to doe thus, wee are not able to beare this ſaile, elſe God would give it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> If this be ſo, let every Soule take his part and portion: All you ſtout diſobedient ſpirits, that will not obey the Goſpell of God, all hearts not broken, and ſpirits not humbled, I have nothing to ſay to you for the while: But you that have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny obedience of the worke of the ſpirit, and grace in your Soules, you that are now willingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d, and reſolutely perſwaded to give way to Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> and breake open doore to a Saviour: if there be any Soule that hides himſelfe according to the former doctrine, you humble, broken
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4400:13"/> hearted ſinners, goe your wayes with comfort, and the God of heaven goe with you, nay, hee is with you, hee will meet with you at home, nay, hee will meet with you in the mid-way; what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thy ſinnes, or miſeries, or wants be, here is conſolation, yea abundant conſolation, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the heart, if thou beeſt a poore broken hearted ſinner, it is enough, the Lord Chriſt will come into your ſoules, and let then what will, or can come, the Lord Jeſus will come, and that ſuddenly. But you will ſay, So many are the ſinnes that lye upon mee, my corruptions like clouds, come in upon mee, all my oathes and drunkenneſſe, all pride, and looſeneſſe, and vanitie, and earthly mindedneſſe, all my corruptions come in upon mee, and the guilt remaines, and they are not pardoned: their horror remaines, and I cannot get my ſoule pacified in the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the forgiveneſſe of them: that pride, and adultery, and drunkenneſſe, army after army, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion after Legion of ſinnes, preſſe in upon mee. Are your ſoules thus perplexed with miſeries? why, I beſeech you, conſider what I ſay: art thou humbled thou polluted heart? art thou oppreſſed with thy corruptions? doth thy ſoule ſay, it is the greateſt burthen I have, the greateſt wound I feele; if my heart were but rid of my ſinnes, my ſoule ſhould be quiet, and my heart pacified; why then, If the Lord ſeeth thee humbled, hee will never ſee thee corrupted, hee will come ſuddenly: let all thy corruptions come accuſing, let all thy ſinnes riſe up at armes againſt thee: yet if thy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4400:14"/> heart be broken for theſe, and humbled in the conſideration of theſe, and reſolved to forſake them, the Lord will come ſuddenly, and then mercy will come to pardon all, to ſubdue all theſe curſed diſtempers that hang upon thee: But you will ſay, What, will this Lord come into my ſoule, this wretched ſoule, theſe mud-walls, this abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable heart; what to mee, will the Lord come to my temple? ſuch hideous ſinnes have I commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Lord come into ſuch a rotten cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and ſuch a baſe curſed heart as mine? Aye, marke what the text ſaith, <hi>I ſtand at the doore and knock; If any man will open, I will come in.</hi> Hee knocks at the doore of every proud perſon, and adulterer, and drunkard: if any adulterous perſon will open, the Lord will come and ſanctifie him: If any uncleane wretch will open, the Lord will come and releaſe him from all abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: what a comfort is this then? let Satan accuſe us, and ſinne condemne us, if the Lord will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us, who can diſcourage us? if the Lord will ſave us, who can condemne us? Againe, as this is comfort againſt all ſinnes, ſo there is marvellous comfort againſt all extremities and miſeries: If thou art humbled, let miſeries come, and troubles and temptations come, and Chriſt will come too, into an humble Soule, in all weakneſſes, Chriſt will come, to ſtrengthen in all diſgraces: and will come to honour thee, here is comfort: The favour of men goeth away, the neerer a man goeth to God, the farther they goe from him, hee is a ſtranger now to his brother, and an aliant to his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4400:14"/> mothers Sonne: why, let thy wants be what they will, and let troubles come, and weakneſſe come, though they come, the Lord will not goe away; though friends be farre off, the Lord will be neere unto thee: Be therefore comforted, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the wiſe man ſaith, a man will change ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to get a commoditie, ſometimes hee will part with honour, for profit, and money will ſupply all; whatſoever the world can doe, money can doe. Therefore this quiets the rich man; I have it by mee, I have many wants, that is no matter, I have it by mee in money: haply hee wants a houſe, thats no matter, hee hath it by him in money, and therefore can build him one: hee wants cloathes to cloath him; but hee hath it in money, and that will buy them, (thus money anſwers to all.) You that are broken hearted ſinners goe home chearfully, eat your bread with glad hearts: the Lord accepts you, and how ever men will not looke after you, but looke aloofe: goe home, and the Lord comfort you more and more, know the Lord Chriſt comes ſuddenly and anſwers to all; it was the ſpeech of Chriſt to his Diſciples: <hi>Feare not little flock, it is your Fathers will to give you a Kingdome:</hi> You are troubled, you ſhall have a Kingdome, that will quiet you: you are diſgraced, you ſhall have a Kingdome, that will honour you: you are in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, you ſhall have a Kingdome, that will comfort you. Let an humble Soule goe downe into the Sea, and fly into the uttermoſt parts of the earth, yet it will comfort thee, the Lord will
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4400:15"/> come ſuddenly, and bring his proviſion with him; whereſoever thou art, hee will be with thee, to comfort thee and cheare thee. You little ones that are humbled, it is not your Fathers pleaſure only to give you a Kingdome, but his Sonne and hee anſwers all: what though thou haſt many miſeries? thou haſt a Chriſt that is the God of all mercies: thou haſt many ſinnes, what of that? thou haſt a Chriſt, that is the God of all grace; where ever thou art, hee will bee with thee; though thou wert baniſhed, yet he will wander up and downe all the wilderneſſe, but he will find thee and bring thee upon his ſhoulders, to cheare thee, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thee here, and give the end of thy hopes here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: If wee be not comforted hereby, it is a ſhame, therefore let every ſad Soule take his part: if you have Chriſt, you have enough, though you never ſee good day after.</p>
            <p>Now wee come to the ſecond doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> When the Lord Jeſus comes to the humbled Soule, hee takes poſſeſſion of it as his owne: now when the ſoule is at Gods diſpoſe, that mercy may doe what it will with him: and then the Lord takes poſſeſſion, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.8.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Wherein lies the Soveraigne poſſeſſion?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> It appeares in two particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The Lord Jeſus undertakes for the Soule.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Hee diſpoſeth of it to his beſt advantage.</p>
            <p>Hee undertakes for it, (namely) hee takes upon him, to ſhelter it from all the evill which it could not avoid: I told you before, the ſinner ſees his vileneſſe of ſinne, and deſires now to be freed,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4400:15"/> but cannot deliver himſelfe, and therefore ſues to Chriſt. Now our Saviour ſteps in, and ſaies, hee will undertake to pay all: If men be oppreſſed with ſome outragious enemy, they ſeeke to ſome ſorraigne Prince, and ſubmit to him, if hee will take the protection of them. So when the Soule is oppreſſed with too many ſins, with too heavy pangs, it falls downe and deſires Chriſt to be Lord protectour of it; and then preſently Chriſt comes and frees it from the evill. 35. <hi>Numb.</hi> 25. it was an Injunction, that the man-ſlayer ſhould fly to the Cities of refuge, and they ſhould open the gate to him: the man-ſlayer is the poore ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that is purſued, now hee flies to the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, his refuge (as <hi>David</hi> often ſpeakes.) Now Chriſt receives and delivers him from the hand of the avenger. The dangers of an humble heart are three, for which Chriſt undertakes; firſt, the juſtice of the Father not ſatisfied; ſecondly, the temptation of Satan not conquered; thirdly, Sinne, not yet ſubdued: All theſe the Soule ſinkes under, and cries, who will deliver mee: when the heart is thus, Chriſt is come to reſcue it, and ſaith, be comforted: the juſtice of my Father I will ſatisfie, the malice of Satan I will croſſe, the power of corruption I will caſhiere.</p>
            <p>The ſinner ſees a juſt God, that will have his <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> glory: when thus juſtice makes out, Chriſt puts in Bale. When a man is areſted, if ſome great man give his word, hee is acquitted: ſo when the venome of Gods vengeance purſues thee, Chriſt paſſeth his word, hee will ſee all ſatisfied, bee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4400:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:4400:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:4400:17"/> therefore comforted, Chriſts word will goe, hee deſires no other pacifier.</p>
            <p>Temptation is ſubdued, ſinne and Satan muſt give way: That ſupreme authority makes ſinne and Satan vaniſh. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.18. A key is an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of authority, he that hath the Key, may let in and ſhut out whom hee will. So Chriſt can bring out whom he will, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. Looke how Conquerours lead captived ſlaves, ſo Chriſt leads ſinne and death, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.18. When the Scepter of Chriſt was diſplayed, Satan fell like lightning.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Sinne comes to be caſhiered, ſinne pleads pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription in the Soule, and challenges a title; yet Chriſt having taken poſſeſſion, hee will have all charges; when ſinne ſaith, I have poſſeſſed the Soule from my youth, therefore why ſhould I out, Chriſt replies, it is uſurped, all this title is but forged, it is mine, and I come for my owne, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſinne depart, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. Chriſt condemnes ſinne in the fleſh: to condemne ſinne, is as much as, when a man hath caſt in his cauſe, hee layes claime to a thing, and is caſt by law. So ſinne layes claime to the Soule: and Chriſt comes and condemnes ſinne in the fleſh: Hee makes the cauſe goe againſt ſinne: for ſinne claimes right on this ground, every ſonne of <hi>Adam</hi> is the childe of diſobedience, he is under my power, and death is his due from mee. Now Chriſt anſwers, Thoſe for whom the ſinne of <hi>Adam</hi> hath beene ſatisfied, over thoſe ſin hath no poſſeſſion: but the Soule is ſuch; doth <hi>Adams</hi> ſin remaine? I have ſatisfied
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4400:17"/> for it. Is ſinne ſtrong? I have led captivity cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: thus ſinne loſeth his cauſe, this is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne ſinne in the fleſh, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. Firſt they were turned from the power of Sathan, and then followed remiſſion of ſinnes, and ſanctification.</p>
            <p>Hee diſpoſes of the Soule for his beſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> when Satan the ſtrong man kept the houſe, and the ſoule was at his manage, and tillage, it either lay fallow ground, as <hi>Ier.</hi> 4.3. overſpread with thornes. When ſinne and Satan rule the heart, they blinde it, and the whole entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on our part, as God calls, ſo the Soule en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaines that call: and that appeares in two things.</p>
            <p>The ſinner receives the worke of grace and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> mercy, being empty: The Lord may powre in what he will, there is roome in the Soule to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine any thing: and this is called paſſive receiving, namely hereby God fits the Soule to receive mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and prepares it, that it may come, and the ſoule being emptied, entertaines the worke of mercy.</p>
            <p>The ſoule being emptied, and having received <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> vertue from God, returnes an anſwer to this call; and this we call active calling. The ſoule having received power, by vertue of that power returnes an anſwer to the call of God, as it is with an ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho; firſt the ayre is moved by the voice, ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, being moved it returnes the ſame voice: So it is with the anſwer of the Soule, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.8. Like that of the men of <hi>Syria</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.32.33. When <hi>Ahab</hi> ſaid, my brother <hi>Benhadad,</hi> ſo the ſinner waits and lookes, when will God have mercy, at laſt God ſaith, my ſonne, and the Soule anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4400:18"/> thy Sonne Lord, <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.22. marke how they anſwer: Behold wee come, for thou art the Lord our God: The Lord ſaith, come away, and the Soule ſaith, behold I come, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. Its the ſame voyce that ecchos, the ſame beame that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects from the wall: So it is the ſame ſpirit that returnes the voyce: and this anſwer of the Soule, wee tearme faith. Now wee have cut out our worke, and for the further handling, we have choſen this text, which is, to diſcover this worke of vocation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4400:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
